Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Maritime Union of America PE 008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Maritime Union of America
1937-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
Will, Gary D.
Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991
PE 008
4 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Maritime Union of America (NMU) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the staff of the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The NMU was founded in 1937, in large measure by former members of the Commnist-led Marine Workers Industrial Union. Purged of its Communist leadership in 1948, the NMU eventually merged with the Seafarers International Union of North America in 2001. The files contain a variety of documents such as newspaper clippings, flyers, brochures, biographical material, convention proceedings, chapter and ships' meeting minutes, correspondence, and other items.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within the series.
Organized in one series.
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Maritime Union of America, which represented workers in the merchant marine, was formed in 1937, as a split from the International Seafarer's Union, which was affiliated with the American Federation of Labor (AFL). At it's first convention in 1937, the NMU joined the Committee for Industrial Organizations (CIO). A crucial role in its formation was played by former members of the Communist-led Marine Workers Industrial Union. Among the notable reforms achieved by the union's Communist-dominated leadership was "checkerboarding," the side-by-side racial integration of sailors' sleeping quarters. The union was led by Joseph Curran, who served for as NMU president until 1981, at which time it was discovered he was to receive a lump sum payment of his pension of $2 million. He eventually agreed to take monthly payments in lieu of the lump sum. During World War II, the alliance of Communists and non-communists in the union was weakened by charges that the Communists, in their desire to maximize productivity to aid the Soviet Union, did not aggressively defend sailors' interests. The Cold War and organized labor's stance thereto exacerbated the ideological divide, and in 1948, the NMU's Communist leadership and its allies were defeated in union elections, then expelled, and subsequently deprived of their sailor's papers by the U.S. Coast Guard. The union was weakened by the loss of these militant members, the rise of foreign-based flag of convenience shipping companies (which drastically reduced NMU membership from its WWII high of over 80,000 members), and internal corruption. Despite this, in 1950, the NMU's Welfare plan was established, providing seamen with health, accident and life insurance benefits. In 1954 a pension component was added. Curran's successor, Shannon Wall, was not well- received my a strong minority of the union, led by James Morrissey, who had run against Wall in previous elections and been attacked and beaten outside the union headquarters in 1966. The Union had members in Panama, the Great Lakes, as well as the East and Gulf Coasts of the United States. In 2001, the NMU merged with the Seafarers International Union of North America, which originally represented West Coast merchant mariners.
Conditions Governing Access
Edward Hendrickson NMU Papers in Box 4 contain sensitive materials and are restricted to researchers.
The rest of the materials are open without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Maritime Union and Seafarers International Union: Reference Files of the Seafarers International Union, WAG 267
Custodial History
The provenance of this material is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff. Some of the papers are personal in nature - correspondence, campaign materials, and may have come from James Morrissey or one of his colleagues.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Maritime Union of America consists of papers relating to the activities of the Union and is rich in documenting the politics, including the fierce and at times violent internal struggles between Left and Right factions, personalities, and daily life of the members of the Union. The files contain a variety of documents such as newspaper clippings, flyers, brochures, biographical material, convention proceedings, chapter and ships' meeting minutes, correspondence, and other items. Much of the collection focuses on the leadership of Joseph Curran, who served as President of the Union for from 1937-1981. Most extensively covered is the 1944-1952 struggle to remove Communist and other Left influence from the union, including lengthy transcripts of sometimes violent ship, local port and national meetings. Among the many contentious topics was the nature of, and whether the NMU should participate in the Committee for Maritime Unity, a 1946-7 initiative of West Coast longshoremen's union leader, the Communist-associated Harry Bridges. Also well documented are subsequent internal conflicts, including efforts led by reformer Joe Morrisey in the 1970s-80s. Two histories of the union are included in the collection and provide a detailed look at the founding and history of the union. Some materials reflect the activity of NMU dissident member Henry Spira (1927-1998), later a leader of the animal rights movement and a formative influence on the ethics philosopher Peter Singer.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library through various donations.
Gary D. Will donated a membership book from the National Maritime Union of America in 2013. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.100.
Stanley Postek donated Edward Hendrickson NMU Papers in 1987. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.071.
Pamphlets.; Fliers (printed matter); Minutes (administrative records); Blacklisting, Labor -- United States.; Constitutions.; Labor union meetings.; Labor unions -- Elections -- United States.; Newsletters.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Memorandums.; Proceedings.; Official reports.; Merchant mariners |z United States; Will, Gary D.; Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991; International Seamen's Union of America; Wall, Shannon; National Maritime Union of America; Marine Workers Industrial Union (U.S.); Smith, Ferdinand; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Morrissey, James
- 25th Anniversary Dinner, 1962; 251216 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Collier Companies, 1946-1948; 251217 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Companies and Agents, 1944-1963; 251218 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Inland Boatmens Division, 1941; 251219 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Ocean-Going Dry Cargo Vessels, 1972-1984; 251220 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Ocean-Going Tanker Vessels, 1978-1984; 251221 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Tanker Companies, 1946-1958; 251222 (Box 1)
- Agreements: Various, 1943, 1955; 251223 (Box 1)
- Arbitration, 1946; 251224 (Box 1)
- Bell, The, Apr 1971; 251225 (Box 1)
- Benefits, 1947-1952, undated; 251226 (Box 1)
- Benefits: Pamphlets and Publications, 1953, 1957, undated; 251227 (Box 1)
- Blacklisting, 1950; 251228 (Box 1)
- Board of Trustees, 1960; 251229 (Box 1)
- Boston Branch Minutes, 1938; 251230 (Box 1)
- Call, The, 1966-1969; 251231 (Box 1)
- Circular Letters, 1942, 1959, undated; 251232 (Box 1)
- Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1968; 251233 (Box 1)
- Committee for Democratic Unionism, undated; 251234 (Box 1)
- Committee for the Administration Team: Curran Retirement, 1973; 251235 (Box 1)
- Committee for Union Democracy, 1970; 251541 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1937; 251542 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1945-1949; 251543 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1951-1959; 251544 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1960-1980; 251545 (Box 1)
- Contract: "Currans Sellout Agreement" - "Flip Flop Fink", 1972; 251546 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1947; 251547 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1949; 251548 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1957; 251549 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1960, 1963; 251550 (Box 1)
- Convention Proceedings 16th (I), 1972; 251551 (Box 1)
- Convention Proceedings 16th (II), 1972; 251552 (Box 1)
- Convention: Presidents Report, 1980, 1984; 251553 (Box 2)
- Cooks: Stewards Bulletin, undated; 251554 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Union Members, 1968-1973; 251555 (Box 2)
- Curran, Joseph: Pamphlets and Publications, 1949-1969; 251556 (Box 2)
- Curran, Joseph: "Flip Flop Fink", 1972; 251557 (Box 2)
- Dinko, Andy, 1970-1975; 251558 (Box 2)
- Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1944-1949; 251559 (Box 2)
- Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications: Spanish Language, 1947-1948; 251560 (Box 2)
- Elections, 1950; 251561 (Box 2)
- Elections, 1954-1973; 251562 (Box 2)
- Elections, 1969; 251563 (Box 2)
- Elections, 1973; 251564 (Box 2)
- Election: Morrissey, 1973; 251567 (Box 2)
- Election: Morrissey, Jim v. Curran-Wall, 1961-1973; 251601 (Box 2)
- Election: Morrissey v. Curran - Notes, undated; 251568 (Box 2)
- Elections: Morrissey - Panama, 1973; 251565 (Box 2)
- Elections: Panama, 1973; 251566 (Box 2)
- Fighting Fund, 1963; 251569 (Box 2)
- Financial Report, 1941-1943; 251570 (Box 2)
- Financial Reports, 1949-1953; 251571 (Box 2)
- Financial Reports, 1953-1957; 251572 (Box 2)
- France: Port and Dock Union, 1950; 251573 (Box 2)
- General Counsel: Pamphlets and Publications, 1946, undated; 251574 (Box 2)
- History, 1956, 1967, undated; 251575 (Box 2)
- History: "The Communists and the NMU" by Peter Filardo, NYU., undated; 291281 (Box 2)
- Independent Caucus, 1949, undated; 251576 (Box 2)
- Inter-Office Memoranda, 1968; 251577 (Box 2)
- Joseph Curran Building, 1963-1964; 251578 (Box 2)
- Joseph Curran Scholarship Program, 1961; 251579 (Box 2)
- Labor Organization Financial Report, 1962-1972; 251580 (Box 2)
- Litigation, 1969; 251581 (Box 2)
- Local 153, 1961; 251582 (Box 2)
- Local 333, 1963; 251583 (Box 2)
- Local 342, 1966; 251584 (Box 2)
- Local 670: Stationary Engineers, Firemen, Maintenance and Building Service Union, undated; 251585 (Box 2)
- Local 1735, 1953-1956; 251586 (Box 2)
- Marine Leasing Inc: Dual Wage Standards, 1967; 251587 (Box 2)
- Mariner's Magazine, 1952; 251588 (Box 2)
- Meetings: at Sea, Various Ships, 1968-1969; 251589 (Box 2)
- Meetings: General, 1968-1971; 251590 (Box 2)
- Meetings: Joint, 1968-1969; 251591 (Box 2)
- Meetings: Regular Membership, 1946; 251592 (Box 3)
- Meetings: Regular Membership, 1949-1972; 251596 (Box 3)
- Membership, 1953, undated; 251597 (Box 3)
- Membership Committee, 1947-1954, undated; 251598 (Box 3)
- Morrissey, James: Correspondence, 1967-1970; 251599 (Box 3)
- Morrissey, James: Ibrahim v. Curran et al, 1980; 251600 (Box 3)
- Morrissey, James: Papers, circa 1972; 251602 (Box 3)
- Morrissey, James: Campaign (I), 1973; 251603 (Box 3)
- Morrissey, James: Campaign (II), 1973; 251611 (Box 3)
- National Council, 1946; 251612 (Box 3)
- National Council, 1947-1948; 251613 (Box 3)
- National Council: Meeting Proceedings, 1953; 251615 (Box 3)
- National Council: Meeting, 1966; 251616 (Box 3)
- National Council: Meeting, 1969; 251620 (Box 3)
- National Council: President's Report: Joe Curran, 1947; 251614 (Box 3)
- National Council: Subcommittee on Policy Enforcement, 1946; 251621 (Box 3)
- National Headquarters: Correspondence, 1947-1971; 251622 (Box 3)
- NMU Democracy: Anti "Curran-Wall Machine", 1973; 251623 (Box 3)
- National Shipping Rules, 1958, 1978; 251624 (Box 3)
- Newsletter, 1965-1973; 251625 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1944; 251626 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1947; 251627 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1948; 251630 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles: "How Our Seamen Bounced the Commies" The Saturday Evening Post, 1948; 251628 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1949; 251728 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles: Strike, 1949-1950; 251738 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1950; 251729 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1959-1963; 251730 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1965-1966; 251731 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1967; 251732 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1968; 251733 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles: Curran Leadership Issues, 1968; 251741 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1969; 251734 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1970-1971; 251735 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1972-1973; 251743 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1973-1974; 251744 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1975; 251736 (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2005, undated; 251737 (Box 4)
- New York Port: Union Book Selling Racket, 1954; 251739 (Box 4)
- Pamphlet, Clippings: "Our Visit to the U.S.S.R.", 1960; 251745 (Box 4)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1939-1945, undated; 251747 (Box 4)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1944-1961; 251748 (Box 4)
- Panama, 1968; 251746 (Box 4)
- Panama Elections: Circular Letters, undated; 251740 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans, 1950-1955; 251749 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans, 1956-1960; 251750 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans, 1972; 251751 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Retirement Planning Publications, 1958-1962; 251752 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Clippings and Articles, 1967; 251753 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Clippings and Articles, 1968; 251754 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Clippings and Articles, 1969; 251755 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Memoranda and Minutes, 1961-1966; 251756 (Box 4)
- Pension and Welfare Plans: Report: United States Department of Commerce, 1971; 251757 (Box 4)
- Perry, William: Pension, 1966-1972; 251758 (Box 4)
- The Pilot: Rank and File:, 1953; 251759 (Box 4)
- Pilot, Education and Publicity Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1946-1947; 251760 (Box 4)
- Pilot, Education and Publicity Department: Pamphlets and Publications: Spanish Language, 1947; 251761 (Box 4)
- Port Light/Port Lite, 1947, 1972-1973; 251762 (Box 4)
- Port of New York, 1947-1954; 251763 (Box 4)
- Press Clippings, 1971-1972; 251764 (Box 4)
- Rules: Shipping, 1950-1972; 251765 (Box 4)
- S.S. Arlene, 1966; 251766 (Box 4)
- S.S. Eric K. Holzer, 1970-1972; 251767 (Box 4)
- S.S. Santa Paula, 1968; 251768 (Box 4)
- S.S. Santa Rosa, 1969; 251769 (Box 4)
- "Seasons Greetings" Cards, 1943, 1965; 251770 (Box 4)
- Smith, Ferdinand C.: Defense Committee, 1948; 251771 (Box 4)
- Spanish Language material, 1937-1973; 251772 (Box 4)
- United Rank and File Committee, 1950-1967, unrated; 251773 (Box 4)
- Union Leadership: Anti-Curran, 1969; 251742 (Box 3)
- Union of Office and Professional Workers, 1948-1950; 251774 (Box 4)
- United Seamen's Service, 1965; 251775 (Box 4)
- Wages, 1964-1969; 251776 (Box 4)
- Wages: Disbursements to Officers and Employees, 1967-1972; 251777 (Box 4)
- Wirtz v. National Maritime Union, 1968; 251778 (Box 4)
- Edward Hendrickson NMU Papers, 1937-1969 (Box 4)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Repository permission is required for access - contains health records.